David Alan Richards Collection of Rudyard Kipling
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
David Alan Richards Collection of Rudyard Kipling
1869-2007
1894-1936
GEN MSS 1143
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
6.13
(15 boxes) + 8 art, 1 broadside
Richards, David Alan, 1945-
Arrangement
Organized into thirteen groupings: May 2004 Acquisitions, February 2005 Acquisition, October 2008 Acquisition, November 2008 Acquisition, October 2009 Acquisition, November 2010 Acquisition, September 2011 Acquisition, November 2013 Acquisition, August 2014 Acquisition, November 2014 Acquisition, October 2015 Acquisition, December 2016 Acquisition, and July 2017 Acquisition.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of David Alan Richards, 2004-2017.
Rudyard Kipling (1865-1936)
Rudyard Kipling (1865-1936), the English author, was born in Bombay, India, on 30 December 1865, to John Lockwood Kipling, professor in the Sir Jamsetjee Jeejeebhoy School of Art in Bombay, India, and his wife, Alice (Macdonald) Kipling. Kipling was sent to England at the age of five, where he boarded and schooled until he took a job at a newspaper, the Civil and Military Gazette, in Lahore, Pakistan, in 1882. He started publishing stories in the 1880s while working at the Gazette and later at the Pioneer. He returned to England briefly in 1889 and then travelled and settled in the United States for several years. He continued to write prolifically during the 1890s, and by the time he returned to England in late 1896, he was already very well-known. In 1902 Kipling settled at "Bateman's" in Burwash, East Sussex, where he resided until his death on 18 January 1936.
Additional biographical information can be found in standard print and online sources.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The David Alan Richards Collection of Rudyard Kipling consists of material by and relating to English author Rudyard Kipling. There are autograph and typescript letters, signed, from Kipling to others as well as some third-party letters relating to Kipling or the collection. Correspondents include Edward Bok, Ladies Home Journal, Sir Philip Burne-Jones, Moncure D. Conway, C. S. Jarvis, John Lockwood Kipling, A. E. W. Mason, H. Cotton Minchin, S. S. McClure Company, E. W. Stoddard, and others. Writings include a corrected typescript draft of Kipling's first novel, The Light that Failed (1890), an autograph manuscript draft and illustrations for The Princess in the Pickle-bottle, and autograph manuscript and typescript drafts of a number of poems. In addition, there are illustrated works by Kipling's father, John Lockwood Kipling, and a bibliography of Kipling's work. Other papers include scrapbooks, consisting chiefly of clippings, photographs, postcards and other printed ephemera, artwork, and memorabilia relating to Kipling.
Authors, English -- 19th century -- Archives; Authors, English -- 20th Century -- Archives; Photographic prints; Authors; Richards, David Alan, Yale 1967, Yale 1967; Bok, Edward William, 1863-1930; Burne-Jones, Philip, 1861-1926; Conway, Moncure Daniel, 1832-1907; Jarvis, C. S. (Claude Scudamore), 1879-1953; Kipling, John Lockwood, 1837-1911; Kipling, Rudyard, 1865-1936; Mason, A. E. W. (Alfred Edward Woodley), 1865-1948; Minchin, H. Cotton; Richards, David Alan, 1945-; Stoddard, E. W. (Elijah Woodward), 1820-1913; S.S. McClure Company (New York, N.Y.)
- May 2004 Acquisitions, 1911-1936; 3
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically by accession.
  Scope and Contents
  The 2004 Acquisitions consists of letters from Rudyard Kipling to others.
  Former call number: Uncat Ms Vault Kipling.
  - Jarvis, C. S. (Claude Scudamore), 1929-1936 (Box 1)
  - Minchin, H. Cotton, 1928-1929 (Box 1)
  - Unidentified, 1911 (Box 1)
- February 2005 Acquisition, 0.42; (1 box)
  The 2005 Acquisition consists of a corrected draft of Kipling's first novel, The Light that Failed, bound together with an autograph letter, signed, from Kipling to an unidentified editor at Lippincott's Magazine.
  Former call number: Uncat MSS 743.
  - The Light that Failed, draft, typescript and typescript carbon, corrected, with proofreaders' marks, circa 1890; 2 (Box 1)
- October 2008 Acquisition, 1906-1926; 0.21; (1 box)
  Former call number: Uncat MSS 1047.
  Arranged alphabetically.
  - Autograph letter, signed, from Kipling to [Anthony Hope Hawkins], undated (Box 2)
  - "Bibliography of Works by Rudyard Kipling" by Lloyd Chandler, autograph manuscript and typescript, 1926; 6 (Box 2)
  - Royalty contracts, 1906, 1910 (Box 2)
- November 2008 Acquisition, 1908-1933; 2
  Former call number: Uncat Ms Vault File.
  - Autograph letter, signed, from Kipling to "Lady Sackville", 1933 December 6 (Box 2)
  - Typed letter, signed, from E. M. Blaikie to H. F. H. Caldwell, 1908 November 28 (Box 2)
- October 2009 Acquisition, 1
  Former call number: Uncat MSS 1236.
  - The Princess in the Pickle-bottle, illustrations, undated (Box 3 (Broadside))
- November 2010 Acquisition, 1893-1911; 0.21; (1 box)
  Arranged alphabetically by material type.
  The November 2010 Acquisition features Mary C. Ensor's papers relating the Kipling family. Mary C. Ensor's father was the Kipling family doctor and Mary received drawing lessons from John Lockwood Kipling. The Ensor papers include correspondence, an autograph book, and numerous original drawings by John Lockwood Kipling. There are approximately eighteen autograph letters, signed, from different members of the Kipling family to Mary and Dr. Ensor.
  Former call number: Uncat MSS 1255.
  - Autograph letters, signed, from Kipling to others, 1905, 1911 (Box 4)
  - Autograph signature, undated (Box 4)
  - Drawings, undated (Box 4)
  - Mary C. Ensor Collection of Kipling, 1893-1910, undated; 4 (Box 4)
  - Photographs of Kipling, 1909, undated (Box 4)
- September 2011 Acquisition, 1869-1936; 0.21; (1 box)
  The 2011 Acquisition includes correspondence, drafts of writings, and photographs. There are autograph and typescript letters, signed, from Kipling to Edward Bok, editor of the Ladies Home Journal, Shane Chichester, and others, as well as a third-party letter from A. E. W. Mason to Doubleday and Company. Writings include a corrected autograph manuscript draft by Kipling of "The Last Rhyme of True Thomas," circa 1894, and "The Rhyme of Johnny Grundy and His Grey Mare" by John Lockwood Kipling. The latter work, dated "Bombay, January 1869," is illustrated.
  There are photographs of Kipling, Kipling's wife Caroline, his parents, and others.
  Former call number: Uncat MSS 1292.
  - Correspondence, 1899-1908; 5 (Box 5)
  - Photographs, circa 1888-1936; 11 (Box 5)
  - Writings, 1869, [1894]; 2 (Box 5)
- November 2013 Acquisition, 1894-2007; 0.92; (3 boxes) + 1 art
  Organized into two subdivisions for Writings and Other Material.
  The November 2013 Acquisition contains drafts and other material relating to writings, a notebook, photographs, memorabilia, and commemorative material relating to Rudyard Kipling.
  - Writings
    - "The Female of the Species," typescript, undated (Box 6)
      General
      Include's "The Mother of the Man" by Hall Caine, typescript
    - The Light that Failed, "Censorship Dialogue Script" for film adaptation, typescript mimeograph, 1939 October 30 (Box 6)
    - "The Literary Beggar" by Sparham Sheldrake, poem, autograph manuscript, signed, 1900 June 5 (Box 6)
    - The Princess in the Pickle-bottle, illustrations, circa 2006 (Box 6)
  - Other Material
    - Notebook, circa 1894 (Box 6)
    - Photocopies, undated (Box 6)
    - Photographs, 1909-1957, undated; 8 (Box 6)
    - Postcards, 1903-1945, undated; 5 (Box 6)
    - Stamps, 2002-2007, undated; 4 (Box 6)
    - Silver-plated military cigarette case, undated (Box 7)
    - Pen and ink portrait of Kipling by Stanley D. Lovegrove, signed and framed, 1914 (Box 8 (Art))
    - "Zamzama," scale model of cannon, undated (Box 9 (Art))
- August 2014 Acquisition, 1880s-1944; 3.33; (12 boxes)
  The August 2014 Acquisition contains writings, correspondence, artwork, clippings and printed ephemera, photographs, scrapbooks, and other papers by or relating to Rudyard Kipling. Correspondence includes letters from Kipling to E. W. Stoddard, the publishers S. S. McClure Company, Charles Oman, and others, as well as third-party letters from A. E. W. Mason to Doubleday and Company, from his father John Lockwood Kipling to Monsure D. Conway, and from Sir Philip Burne Jones to Lucy Clifford.
  - Artwork, 1905-[1933]; 2 (Box 10)
  - Bookplates, 1894 (Box 10)
  - Clippings, 1902-1936, undated; 3 (Box 10)
  - Correspondence, [1880s]-1944 undated; 10 (Box 10)
  - Kipling Society ephemera, 1930-1935 (Box 10)
  - Menu, signed and initialed, [1927] (Box 10)
  - Photographs and postcards, undated; 8 (Box 10)
  - Programs, 1933 July (Box 10)
  - Stamps, undated; 14 (Box 10)
  - Writings, undated; 6 (Box 10)
  - "Supplication of the Black Aberdeen," poem, typescript carbon, corrected, undated (Box 11)
  - "To Oblige a Young American Lady," autograph manuscript note, signed, undated (Box 11)
  - "C. J. Rhodes," poem, autograph manuscript, circa 1902 (Box 11)
  - "Bobs," poem, autograph manuscript and printed version, 1893, undated (Box 11)
  - [5 War Poems], drafts, typescript, corrected, and page proofs, circa 1895-1930 (Box 12)
  - "Gehazi," poem, draft, autograph manuscript, corrected, undated (Box 12)
  - Kipling copyright case archive of Augustus Gurlitz, 1899-1901 (Box 12)
  - Photographs, 1898-1905, undated; 5 (Box 13 (Art))
  - Photographs, 1936, undated; 4 (Box 14 (Art))
  - "The Princess in the Pickle-bottle," autograph manuscript, signed and framed, undated (Box 15 (Art))
  - "The Recruit's Progress," draft, autograph manuscript, corrected, undated (Box 15 (Art))
  - Photographs and artwork, undated; 4 (Box 16 (Art))
  - Autograph letter, signed from Kipling to C. Gallop, with portrait engraving of Kipling, framed, 1910, undated (Box 17 (Art))
  - Colored print portrait of Kipling by David Levine, framed, undated (Box 18 (Art))
  - Scrapbook on Kipling assembled by E. T. D. Francis, 1893-1938, undated (Box 19)
  - Scrapbook on World War I, 1914-1918, undated (Box 20)
  - Scrapbook on "Rudyard Kiping, In Memoriam, 1865-1936" (Box 21)
- November 2014 Acquisition, 1871-1924; 0.42; (2 boxes)
  Arranged alphabetically by material type and title.
  The 2014 Addition contains the following material: two autograph letters, signed, from Kipling to others; two autograph manuscript drafts; a printing plate for "The King's Ankus," several photographs of Kipling and family, including his parents and daughters, Josephine and Elsie; and his wife's fan, signed by numerous people during the early 1890s.
  - Autograph letter, signed, from Kipling to Fred M. Hopkins, 1896 March 7 (Box 22)
  - Autograph letter, signed, from Kipling to "Lizzie", 1884 October 2 (Box 22)
  - "The King's Ankus," block plate, undated (Box 22)
  - "Max Desmarets: His Valentine," autograph manuscript, 1884 February 14 (Box 22)
  - Menu, autograph manuscript, with drawings, [1890?] (Box 22)
  - "Puck [of?] Pook's Hill," poem, autograph manuscript, signed, undated (Box 22)
  - Photographs, 1871-1924, undated; 7 (Box 22)
  - "Trix's Fan," signed, 1891-1895, undated (Box 23)
  - Vendor descriptions, undated (Box 23)
- October 2015 Acquisition, 1895, undated; 4
  One autograph letter, signed, dated April 11, 1895, from Rudyard Kipling to "Dear Clarke," and one autograph letter, signed, from John Lockwood Kipling to "Dear Margot."
  - Autograph letter, signed, from Rudyard Kipling to "Dear Clarke", 1895 April 11 (Box 23)
  - Autograph letter, signed, from J. L. Kipling to "Dear Margot", undated (Box 23)
  - "The legs of Sister Ursula," draft, autograph manuscript, corrected and signed, undated; 2 (Box 23)
- December 2016 Acquisition, 1924-1934, undated; 0.42; 1 box
  - Facsimile of autograph letter, signed, dated March 7 1896, from Kipling to Fred M. Hopkins, undated (Box 24)
  - Photostat of autograph letter, signed, dated October 26 1887, from Kipling to an unidentified recipient, undated (Box 24)
  - Typescript letter, signed, from Chandler to "Dear Maitland", 1934 May 12 (Box 24)
  - "Talk on the Kipling Society in the United States... by L.H. Chandler", 1931 June 9 (Box 24)
  - "Kipling versus Fenno: A complication of extracts from the legal papers covering this suit", undated (Box 24)
  - Copies of Circuit Court documents relating to "Kipling v. Fenno", undated (Box 24)
  - Gift descriptions, undated (Box 24)
  - Empty case, undated (Box 24)
- July 2017 Acquisition, 1890-1895; 2
  - Autograph manuscript letter, initialed, to "My dear McClure", 1890 June 22 (Box 24)
  - Autograph note, signed, from Julian Ralph, 1895 Jan 26 (Box 24)